Stephen it's a paradox and the Paradox
is this is that when we lower
testosterone the PSA levels will go down
but yet when we give testosterone to men
with normal levels of testosterone even
in super physiologic doses it has no
effect on
PSI welcome back to the trt and hormone
optimization YouTube channel and as a
guest in high demand back with this is
Dr Kei Nichols welcome back ke hey great
to see you again Stephen been a lot of
fun Hi man welcome back and um today
let's talk about maybe one of the
biggest myths concerning trt and that's
the one about prostate cancer so let's
talk about that today I'm sure you get a
lot of questions regarding prostate
cancer in your Facebook group and and
you know other places there's not a a
week that goes by that I don't see a new
patient that was told by their family
doctor or their internist or the
endocrinologist that testosterone was
going to either cause prostate cancer or
or increase their risk of getting it or
make it worse if they had it and it's
interesting to find out where these
beliefs come from so I think it's
important that everybody understand
testosterone and prostate cancer more
specifically the history of Dr Huggins
Dr Morgan toer and the saturation model
now Stephen this is probably one of my
favorite slides when it comes to
testosterone therapy or even hormone
replacement therapy and that is the
problem is not that people are
uneducated the problem is that they are
educated just enough to believe what
they they've been taught and not
educated enough to question what they
have been taught yeah as you and I both
know there's a lot of misinformation
that goes on into the testosterone
replacement therapy field there are
plenty of myths out there that we're
going to discuss the first being
testosterone and prostate cancer and as
you know there are other myths that
we're going to discuss in the upcoming
weeks which include the need for estr
management in testosterone therapy as
well as the harm from the secondary AR
cytosis when one takes testosterone
which is the increase in hemoglobin and
hematocrit that occurs it's in fact the
most common side effect so so much much
information misinformation out there on
those three topics prostate cancer
estradi management and then the
secondary arthrosis yeah all right well
Stephen the belief for over seven
decades now has been that high
testosterone causes prostate cancer or
increases a man's risk of developing
Prost cancer and that low testosterone
is protective against prostate cancer
yeah it was also thought that if you
raise testosterone levels you would
cause an existing prostate cancer to
grow rapidly the equivalent of pouring
gasoline on a fire we've all heard that
now where did this so-called Androgen
hypothy originate well it originated in
1941 there was a paper written that year
by two urologists doors Huggins and Dr
hog Hodes now Dr Huggins was a very
well-known urologist in fact he went on
to win the Nobel Peace Prize in 1966 for
his work with hormones and Cancers and
even to this day he's considered one of
the pain Saints of of Urology so in
1941 this is their study studies on
prostate cancer the effect of castration
of estrogen and of Androgen injection on
serum phosphatases in metastatic
carcinoma of the
prostate now
in this paper they looked at men with
metastatic prostate cancer now back then
they didn't have a PSA test like we do
now so they looked at something kind of
similar which was called prostate acid
phosphatase and they used this as a
serum marker for metastatic prostate
cancer now in this study Dr Huggins
reported that when men were castrated
either surgically or chemically that
these acid phosphatase levels would go
down he also gave men testosterone
injections and he reported that in every
man that he got testosterone gave
testosterone injections to that this
acid phosphatase level would go up so in
other words if they gave them
testosterone this marker for prostate
cancer would rise but when he castrated
them brought their testosterone levels
down that serum acid phosphotase would
go down now this was an important paper
at the time because this was actually
the first paper that identified a cancer
to be hormonally sensitive and it did
establish three things at the time that
Pro aate acid phosphatase could be used
as a serum marker for metastatic
prostate cancer that castration was
effective for metastatic prostate cancer
and that testosterone injections given
to men with metastatic prostate cancer
was
dangerous now when we take a closer look
at this paper you'll see that
testosterone injections were only given
to three
men results were only given for two of
those men and one of those men had been
surgically castrated so he was no longer
hormonally intact and what one would
call hormonally or Androgen
deprived and these are the this is the
report of the two men that he did give
the results from and they gave he gave
them by the their abbreviations of their
name CB and OA CB had already been
surgically castrated so he was no longer
hormonally intact but OA was hormonally
intact and he was given testosterone
propriate injections 25 milligrams for
18 days and these are his serum acid
phosphatase levels that were measured
represented by the solid line here as
you can see very
erratic so the general conclusion that
cancer of the prostate is activated by
Androgen
injections was based on one hormonally
intact patient who received testosterone
injections as I said for 18 days whose
acid phosphatase levels went up and down
and were essentially
uninterpretable so l Lally Decades of
depriving men of testosterone was based
on the over interpretation of the
results of one single man in one study
that you just
saw so most people will ask well well
how can that occur that it really
doesn't make sense well it's easily
explained in the fact by the fact that
in 1940s and 1950s there were not many
Physicians that had experience utilizing
testosterone and no one had any adequate
knowledge to really question the results
so this paper became Dogma that testost
was dangerous for the prostate and
caused prostate cancer now it wasn't
until the 1990s that Harvard urologist
by the name of Abraham Morgan toer began
to question the validity of this angen
hypothesis so in
1988 he began treating men with sexual
dysfunction who had low testosterone
with testosterone now treatment options
were limited for these men at that time
because there wasn't any Calis or biag
so he was going to utilize testosterone
to try to improve their sexual function
but what he noticed is not only did they
improve sexually but they improved both
physically and mentally now you've got
to understand how Brave this man was
because his treatment at that time
defied standard medical care because in
the 1980s testosterone therapy was
really limited to three groups of men
men who had congenital or genetic
disorders like Klein felters uh
pituitary disorders or those that had
absent testes from injury or Illness but
nonetheless he did become concerned
because his colleagues were warning him
that he could potentially be causing
harm to these people based on the work
of Dr
Huggins so in 1992 he began performing
biopsies prior to giving men
testosterone in men that were
symptomatic due to testosterone
deficiency but who had normal PSAs and
normal disal exams now what he was
trying to do is real out an existing
prostate cancer so it wouldn't be like
pouring gasoline on a
fire now what he found was that 11 of
the first 77 men that he biopsy had
prostate
cancer now remember low testosterone was
supposed to be protective against
prostate cancer and what he found was
that approximately 14% of men with low
testosterone levels had prostate cancer
now Stephen this percentage is almost
the same percentage of men that have
prostate cancer that have increased risk
factors like an increased PSA and a
positive digital rectal exam
he followed up with that study where he
evaluated several hundred more men 345
to be exact and at that time he found
prostate cancer to be present in more
than one of seven hypogonadal men with a
normal PSA an increased risk of prostate
cancer was associated with more severe
reductions in testosterone in other
words the lower the testosterone levels
they had the higher rate of prostate
cancer he
found so low testosterone was found not
to be protective so now we knew that
what about high testosterone levels
being harmful they must be harmful if if
lower is not protective so in 2004 he
published this paper risk of
testosterone replacement therapy and
recommendations for monitoring he
published it in the New England Journal
of Medicine and for that paper he did a
worldwide literature review between 1985
to 2004 looking for any wor some
relationship between testosterone and
prostate cancer or testosterone therapy
in prostate cancer Stephen he was unable
to find one single article that showed
that testosterone increased a man's risk
of getting prostate cancer or the
testosterone therapy caused prostate
cancer
progression he also made the astute
observation that look there was about a
tenfold increase in testosterone
prescriptions around 2001 with the
release of andrel but yet we weren't
seeing an epidemic of prostate cancer
and all these men that were getting test
we also know that around 50% of men aged
50 years or older have microsi of
prostate cancer in their prostates so if
increasing levels of testosterone in the
men was going to cause the cancer to
grow more rapidly then we should have
seen more cancer growth in those men but
we
didn't and the observation has been
right in front of all of us for decades
and that is that younger men with high
testosterone levels don't get prostate
cancer but instead it's a dis disease of
Aging when testosterone levels
declined so in
2007 Dr Morgan Toler developed the
saturation model to make sense of two
opposite observations that the data
reported Stephen it's a paradox and the
Paradox is this is that when we lower
testosterone the PSA levels will go down
but yet when we give testosterone to men
with normal levels of testosterone even
in super physiologic doses it has no
effect on PSA
say now this is the way that most men
view prostate cancer or the prostate
itself and testosterone I even had some
comments at our last at our last video
with DHT and things like that that nope
I took testosterone and my PSA went up
yes sir it it did and we're going to
explain why and how that occurred but
most people view test Stalone and
prostate growth cancerous or
benign via lines a and be that the
higher the testosterone levels then
the the bigger the growth but that's not
how it really occurs it really follows
line C and so let me explain so we do
know that castration a zero level of
testosterone will make the PSA go
down and if you increase testosterone
out of this cast rate range zero the PSA
level will go up
as represented by line
C but the data shows that for most of
the range of testosterone including
superphysiological ranges there's no
change in PSA level or prostate
size Stephen prostate cancer is
exquisitly sensitive to androgens in a
low
concentration where it is Androgen
dependent right here you increase
testosterone PSA is going to go up the
prostate is very sensitive to Androgen
in a low Androgen
environment okay but the prostate
doesn't respond to Androgen
concentrations above the saturation
point there it becomes Androgen
indifferent now why is that now this is
because androgens have a limited ability
to stimulate prostate tissue now in
order for the androgens to exert an
effect on prostate tissue they must
first bond to the Androgen receptor and
once The andren receptors are fully
saturated with Androgen then any
increase will just be in excess now
Stephen the saturation point in the
prostate occurs at a level of around 250
nanograms per deciliter a very low level
of testosterone Above This level
androgens have no further effect on
benign or cancerous prostate tissue
growth so yes if a man initiates
testosterone therapy with a level
outside of the hypogonadal range when
his prostate is already fully saturated
then raising testosterone will have no
effect on benign or cancerous prostate
growth so the man in your previous video
made a comment yes he had a very low
testosterone level he started
testosterone we expect a rise in fact
the guidelines American neurology
Association the endoc society when a man
has a low testosterone level and
initiates
testosterone we can have an acceptable
rise of around 1.5 over Baseline so if
you have a baseline of one his PSA is
one he has a low testosterone level we
know he has a small prostate when he
starts testosterone it's going to cause
it to increase in size up into the
saturation point and an acceptable rise
after starting testosterone is about 1.5
by most guidelines if a man starts
testosterone level starts to sa level
around four or 500 we expect no
significant change at all in his PSA
level so this is the andrin dependent
growth right here so low testosterone
very sensitive to getting testosterone a
level of above
250 no effect fully sat The receptors
are fully saturated all right so so guys
can visualize this a little better Dr
Morgan Toler likes to think of the
prostate like a house plant so he says
if you deprive the plant of water it
will
shrink if you give it water at this
point it's going to grow as represented
by this picture now giving it any
additional water past this point will
have no effect on growth you could
literally give it a constant water
supply and it's never going to grow into
a
tree once that plant's thirst has been
quenched giving it any additional water
will have no effect on growth and the
same goes for testosterone and the
prostate so that is the saturation model
that explains that
Paradox
so what does the Moder modern uh medical
literature show us about testosterone
prostate
cancer test testosterone therapy does
not increase the risk of developing
prostate cancer even in high-risk
individuals Stephen it may in fact have
a
protective role against high-grade
cancer and Studies have shown that
higher levels of testosterone can
suppress prostate cancer growth in fact
there is an inverted U with regard to
prostate cancer cell proliferation and
testosterone levels at low testosterone
levels there are suppression of prostate
cancer cell proliferation between
castrate levels zero and 250
the hypogonadal range there's actual
growth and with high levels of
testosterone there's once again
suppression of prostate cancer cell
proliferation now this is noted in this
study here done at Baylor where two
different cell lines of prostate cancers
were exposed to different concentrations
of
testosterone and here is your inverted U
the black line represents no
testosterone and then as we move to the
right we're getting increasing levels of
uh testosterone concentrations and these
as you see there's suppression some some
degree of depression suppression here
with no testosterone when they're
exposed to a low concentration of
testosterone so the hypogonadal range
there is increase in proliferation but
with increasing levels of testosterone
concentrations there is suppression of
prostate cancer cell proliferation so
this is the inverted U this is another
representation of both cell
lines A and D
are zero
testosterone B and E are the two cell
lines exposed to a low level of
testosterone point1 nanograms per
milliliter and then when the prostate
cancer cells are exposed to a high level
of testosterone eight nanograms per
milliliter you see there a suppression
of prostate cancer cell
proliferation even more so than castrate
levels
y t testosterone therapy does not
increase the risk of progression in men
on active surveillance in fact low
testosterone is a predictor of who will
progress on active
surveillance testosterone therapy does
not increase the risk of biochemical
recurrence after treatment of prostate
cancer by radiation therapy or radical
prostectomy Studies have actually shown
decreased recurrence rates in Minal
testosterone
therapy multiple Studies have now shown
that low testosterone step low is
associated with an increased risk of
developing prostate cancer and higher
grades of cancer a more advanced stage
of cancer at surgery and an increased
recurrence after surgery it's also
associated with decreased
survival so the current landscape of
testosterone therapy and the setting of
prostate cancer has gone through several
par several Paradigm shifts it's evolved
from viewing testosterone as dangerous
and pouring gasoline on a fire to
thinking it might be safe and but using
it cautiously but now as a protective
measure and as therapy in castrate
resistant prostate cancer we in fact now
use testosterone to treat men with
castrate resistant prostate cancer it's
called bipolar Androgen therapy where
men are treated with high doses of
testosterone followed by no
testosterone so this is where we come
back to the original slide that once
again is my favorite we need to thank
men like Abraham Morgan Toler for the
work he's done with men on uh testost I
consider him the father of testosterone
therapy uh a brilliant brilliant man and
so this is the that history this is
where all the misinformation came from
and this is what the data now shows us
that it's safe and that it's protective
and that low testosterone levels are
what we should avoid and what causes the
harm and increase in morbidity and
mortality and as we discussed at the
beginning of our video we're going to
take this same approach to to
testosterone and estradi management and
the secondary Arroyos is the increase in
hemoglobin and hematocrit from
testosterone testosterone's been used
for 85 years or more it's never caused
harm in any randomized control trial and
the secondary Arroyos has never been
shown to cause harm and we you and I
will be doing a little podcast on this
and that'll be a lot of fun yeah that
was an incredible explanation ke very
clear that explains really the Paradox
well thank you very much Stephen I
appreciate you having me on again I look
forward to seeing you again and doing
more work together sure thing I would
ask the viewers to leave their comments
uh in the section beneath the video and
I'm sure you keep an eye on those as
well